<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Open Health Care UK - Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog.html"/>
  <updated>2016-03-20T22:21:20+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Open Health Care UK]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Make a Great Hack Day Pitch]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2016/03/21/how-to-pitch-at-a-hackday/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-21T15:00:29+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2016/03/21/how-to-pitch-at-a-hackday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We&rsquo;ve been running Hack Days for quite a while now. <a href="http://nhshackday.com">NHS Hack Day</a> has
seen thousands of enthusiastic volunteers through our doors, and hundreds of project pitches.</p>

<p>One of the questions that we get asked a lot, particularly by people who are new to hack days
is</p>

<blockquote class="custom-quote"><p><i class="fa fa-quote-left"></i>
What makes a good pitch at a hack day?
</p></blockquote>


<p>&hellip; so we thought we&rsquo;d share a few tips for people coming to hack days on how to make a great
hack day pitch</p>

<h2>1. Tell a story</h2>

<p>People love stories. Pitches with a story in them almost always go down better. So give it
colour - explain how your life is broken because of this problem, explain the frustrations
of a life without the thing you&rsquo;re pitching.</p>

<p>Particularly when the person who would benefit is some kind of specialist, most of the people
listening to the pitch won&rsquo;t understand what what life is like for the people that your pitch
is about. So help them empathise by telling a story about their experiences.</p>

<h2>2. Explain the change you want to see</h2>

<p>Hack day projects that capture the imagination are mostly the ones with the potential to make
a real impact in the world. That means that when you&rsquo;re pitching, you should make sure to explain
just how the world will be better once you&rsquo;ve made your project.</p>

<p>Sometimes that&rsquo;s a bold vision of the future that brings about the end of global capitalism,
injustice, hunger, and human suffering generally. More often, it&rsquo;s a story about how you can
help lots of people in a small but meaningful way.</p>

<h2>3. Make it achievable</h2>

<p>While we&rsquo;re on the subject of your grand vision for changing the entire world, it&rsquo;s important
to keep in mind that the hack day you&rsquo;re at probably only lasts a day or two. Once you&rsquo;ve taken
out time for pitches, presentations and lunch, the time you have available for building things is
limited.</p>

<p>Because of that, pitches that seem to be too wildly ambitious can be greeted with scepticism -
a sense that they&rsquo;re simply unachievable in the time available. Thankfully, just like the
journey of a thousand miles, huge projects can always be broken down into a sequence of smaller
ones.</p>

<p>If your idea seems huge and overwhelming, <em>you should still talk about it</em> - because it probably
scores big on the &ldquo;have an impact&rdquo; scale we were just talking about. But you should also make
sure to break off an achievable chunk of it, and explain that <em>this</em> is what you want to build
<em>today</em>.</p>

<h2>4. Make it clear</h2>

<p>You&rsquo;re only going to have a very short time for your pitch. Probably no more than a couple minutes.</p>

<p>Keep it snappy.</p>

<p><em>(Note, this section has been heavily edited down in the name of brevity and minimal irony.)</em></p>

<h2>5. Problem first, not solution backwards</h2>

<p>The most powerful hack day experiences come from ideas that are genuinely co-created, in response
to problems or needs that actually exist in the real world. (Hence starting with the story/impact).</p>

<p>A common pitfall of hack day pitches is to skip right over the process of actually problem solving,
and start pitching the detailed solution that first occurred to the person doing the pitching.
Unsurprisingly this tends not to excite the creative problem-solvers in the room. (Hint: those are
<em>exactly</em> the people you want to be working with )</p>

<p>The two <em>particularly</em> common cases of this are &ldquo;Let me tell you the specific screens my
app will have&rdquo; and &ldquo;I have this library/Raspberry Pi/Google Glass&hellip; please make it relevant to
someone.&rdquo;</p>

<h2>6. Practice</h2>

<p>Just like most things in life, pitching is something you can get better at with practice!
Luckily, when you arrive at a hack day, you are often sat around in a big room with a bunch
of other people who you don&rsquo;t know, just waiting for something to happen.</p>

<p>Why not say hello to one of them who you don&rsquo;t know, and ask if you can practice your pitch?
Ask for feedback - what did they like about it? Was there anything that wasn&rsquo;t clear? It&rsquo;s a
good way to make friends in the inevitable down time at the start of the day, and you&rsquo;ll end
up with a better pitch.</p>

<p>For NHS Hack Day, we organise meetups before the event, and invite attendees to come and meet
one another. We make sure that we have some hack day veterans on hand, and we give friendly
constructive feedback to anyone with a project they want to pitch. We also encourage people
to post their ideas to our mailing list.</p>

<h2>7. Try to find some collaborators beforehand</h2>

<p>We&rsquo;ve found that as well as helping to polish ideas, sharing your pitch
on the mailing list beforehand can result in teams that start to form before the day. It
gives potential collaborators a chance to mull the project over in the weeks and days running
up to the event, and come with more fully formed ideas.</p>

<p>These teams often work really well together. They come prepared and already excited, and
when the time comes to start working, they often have the most structure, and the clearest
understanding of what needs to happen. The process of discussing your idea with them will give
you a better idea of what excites people about it and make your pitch better.</p>

<h2>8. Don&rsquo;t make it exploitative</h2>

<p>Hack days are often attended by volunteers in their free time. They&rsquo;re a great space for
creative collaboration, idea generation, skill sharing, and building communities.</p>

<p>They are not free labour for your startup/church f&ecirc;te/government department.</p>

<p>Ask yourself if this is something that might be interpreted as asking someone to just do
free work. If you think it is, consider paying someone to do it instead of pitching at a hack
day. If you&rsquo;re not sure, have a chat with one of the organisers - they&rsquo;ll normally be happy
to give you a steer about what&rsquo;s appropriate at their particular event.</p>

<h2>9. You don&rsquo;t need a mobile app</h2>

<p>Apps. They&rsquo;re great. But&hellip; you almost certainly don&rsquo;t need one. Pitching &ldquo;An iPhone app&rdquo;
is a special case of &ldquo;Don&rsquo;t come with a solution&rdquo; from above. But this one comes up a <em>lot</em>.</p>

<p>The percentage of problems to which the best answer is a native phone app is so close to
zero as to be indistinguishable. Starting with the problem will make your project better.</p>

<p>Related, you might like to read
<a href="https://gds.blog.gov.uk/2013/03/12/were-not-appy-not-appy-at-all/">this blog post</a> from
some nice people at the government about why you don&rsquo;t need an App. Even if you&rsquo;re not the
government, most of that probably still applies.</p>

<h2>10. Bonus points if you avoid Hack Day Bingo.</h2>

<p>There are some kinds of things that come up quite a lot at hack days. They&rsquo;re perfectly
excellent hack day projects. They tend to be the kind of thing that works well in an environment
where you&rsquo;re trying to ship something in a limited time.</p>

<p>That said, primates are suckers for novelty, so you&rsquo;re likely to score bonus points with the room
(particularly the grizzled hack day veterans) if you come up with something that&rsquo;s a little bit new.
Examples of things that have probably been done at least once before are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Something that hits the Twillio API and phones the judges</li>
<li>Taking some data and plotting points on a Google Map</li>
<li>Tinder for dogs/asteroids/_____</li>
<li>Top Trumps for verses of the bible/DNA/______</li>
</ul>


<p><em>(Note: Particular thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/blangry">Alex</a> and
 <a href="https://twitter.com/lily_dart">Lilly</a> for their additions to this list.)</em></p>

<h2>Enough listing already</h2>

<p>So, now you know how to pitch, come join us at the next <a href="http://nhshackday.com">NHS Hack Day</a> and
try it out.</p>

<p><small>
Photo credits: <a href="https://secure.flickr.com/photos/paul_clarke/">Paul Clarke</a>
</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How We're Helping Respond to the Zika Outbreak]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2016/02/16/how-were-helping-respond-to-the-zika-outbreak/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-16T15:00:29+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2016/02/16/how-were-helping-respond-to-the-zika-outbreak</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The last few months have seen an explosive spread of the
<a href="http://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jan/28/zika-virus-spreading-explosively-says-world-health-organisation">Zika virus</a>,
which has been potentially linked to thousands of birth defects in Latin America. The Zika virus is a
<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2016/health/what-is-zika-virus.html">mosquito-transmitted infection</a>
that was previously sporadically reported in Africa and the Pacific, but has recently started spreading rapidly
in South America. Patients usually have a mild flu-like illness consisting of a low fever, headache, muscle and joint pain,
red eyes and rash.</p>

<p>In the UK, many patients who exhibit symptoms related to Zika and have recently travelled are referred to the specialist
<a href="http://www.thehtd.org/">Hospital for Tropical Diseases</a> in London, which has resulted in a large increase in their
workload.</p>

<p>The Hospital for Tropical Diseases uses our <a href="http://elcid.openhealthcare.org.uk/">elCID</a> software to manage their clinical
workflow, so as soon as we heard this,
we tried to understand what we could do to help. At Open Health Care we believe the digital tools clinicians use to do their
jobs need to be iterated and improved on a frequent basis. That means we deliver services that are flexible enough to adapt
to changing clinical needs, and we’re on hand to help make those improvements.</p>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/zika.top.png" alt="" style="border: 1px solid black;"/>
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->


<p>Working closely with clinicians from HTD, we quickly developed a prototype Zika “pathway”. This enables users to record extra
information of particular importance to patients they were treating for Zika, as well as extra quick ways to enter the very
specific set of tests that are most relevant to such patients.</p>

<p>Because we have an electronic clinical pathway specific to the particular condition being treated, we were able to provide
lots of contextually relevant information and notes for its treatment. This guidance was written by the local consultants,
and helps to make sure that every patient is given the very best care possible.</p>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/zika.bottom.png" alt="" style="border: 1px solid black;" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->


<p>All the information about patients that gets entered on <a href="http://elcid.openhealthcare.org.uk/">elCID</a> is stored as high quality
structured data. That means that we
are also able to generate a summary of their interaction with the patient at the click of a button, complete with
symptoms, travel history, investigations and results, and the specific extra Zika information we are now recording.</p>

<p>Documenting clinical activity in this way - on digital tools that understand the clinical domain -  means that it is also
available subsequently for audit and analysis purposes. Extracting data on the management of Zika patients at the hospital
is now something that can be done in a few clicks, rather than requiring a laborious manual review of clinical documentation.</p>

<p>In many ways this is one of the real opportunities of the NHS’ move to paperless working - when you move to using tools that
allow you to analyse and learn from data generated by routine clinical work. We look forward to finding out what the team
learn about their response to the Zika outbreak.</p>

<p>Crucially, this new module involved just a couple of days prototyping, iterating and testing the new Zika pathway, before
deploying to the live system. Over the next few weeks we’ll be checking back regularly to gather feedback from the users
of the service so that we can be sure that we’re meeting their needs.</p>

<p>Updating the systems that underpin the delivery of care should be this simple all the time - they should be designed with
flexibility and iteration in mind, and be supported by teams who have the capability to iterate them responsively.</p>

<p>If you’d like to know more about how we could help you by delivering services like this, or more about the services we offer,
do get in touch with us at <a href="mailto:hello@openhealthcare.org.uk"><a href="&#x6d;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#116;&#111;&#x3a;&#x68;&#x65;&#x6c;&#108;&#111;&#x40;&#111;&#112;&#101;&#110;&#104;&#101;&#97;&#108;&#x74;&#104;&#99;&#97;&#x72;&#x65;&#x2e;&#x6f;&#114;&#103;&#46;&#117;&#107;">&#104;&#101;&#x6c;&#x6c;&#111;&#64;&#x6f;&#112;&#101;&#110;&#104;&#101;&#97;&#x6c;&#x74;&#104;&#x63;&#x61;&#114;&#101;&#x2e;&#111;&#x72;&#103;&#x2e;&#x75;&#x6b;</a></a>.</p>

<p><small>
Photo credits: <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/31031835@N08/">John Tan</a>
</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2015 - Annual Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2016/01/18/annual-review/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-18T15:00:29+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2016/01/18/annual-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>2015 was a big year for us - so we thought we&rsquo;d take a moment and share
some of what we&rsquo;ve been up to:</p>

<h1>Delivering Digital Services for direct care</h1>

<p>We believe that the digital tools used to deliver patient care should be of the highest
possible quality. Not only do we believe it, we work hard to deliver them as well!</p>

<p>Last year we launched two new services - for <a href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/02/05/elcid-opat-launch/">managing OPAT care</a>
at UCLH (patients who need regular IV drugs but aren&rsquo;t so sick that they need to stay in
hospital all the time), and for the returning traveller
<a href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/10/21/launching-a-new-walk-in-service/">walk in clinic</a> at the Hospital for
Tropical Diseases.</p>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/detail.view.png" alt="" style="border: 2px solid black;" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->


<p>We&rsquo;ve also been working to iteratively improve the services we run - conducting user research
interviews, observing clinicians using our tools on the wards, and generally trying to establish
robust feedback loops and processes for users to tell us how we can make things better for them.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">From the wards yesterday: &#10;&#10;&quot;You&#39;re actually coming and asking doctors how you can make the IT systems they use better? - That&#39;s unheard of&quot;</p>&mdash; David Miller (@thatdavidmiller) <a href="https://twitter.com/thatdavidmiller/status/642247781617397760">September 11, 2015</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>Based on this research, we&rsquo;ve made lots of improvements to the UI of our services, coming up
with new design patterns for building applications for direct care in the process.</p>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/list.view.png" alt="" style="border: 2px solid black;" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->


<h1>Code</h1>

<p>Lots of this work invovles us writing, maintaining and improving code.</p>

<p>During 2014 We made 3 major <a href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/11/13/opal-05-released/">new releases</a> of
<a href="http://opal.openhealthcare.org.uk">OPAL</a> - our framework
for building digital services for clnicians, not to mention many other smaller releases,
making up <b>2,416</b> individual commits across all
our <a href="https://github.com/openhealthcare">Open Source projects</a>.</p>

<p>Throughout the year we&rsquo;ve been focussing on making our projects easier for new developers
to pick up - improving the <a href="http://opal.openhealthcare.org.uk/docs">documentation</a> and
refactoring things to provide better APIs for people to build on.</p>

<h1>Hackdays</h1>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/nhshd.10.jpg" alt="" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->


<p>2015 was as busy as ever for <a href="http://nhshackday.com">NHS Hack Day</a>, with three
events bringing together hundreds of clinicians, academics, designers, developers, and
patients to help make the NHS just a little better.</p>

<p>We kicked off the year with another trip to <a href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/05/25/nhs-hack-day-10/">Cardiff</a>,
before coming back to London in May, and then heading up to Manchester in the Autumn.</p>

<h1>UK Health Camp</h1>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/healthcamp.foyer.jpg" alt="" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->


<p>2015 also saw the first <a href="http://ukhealthcamp.com">UK Health Camp</a> - a community unconference
for people interested in digital and data in health and care. We were proud to sponsor the
event, and glad to have a community space to discuss the pressing issues of digital transformation
within the NHS.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re already looking forward to next year, and have started plotting how to make it even more
of a success with the rest of the team!</p>

<h1>The Future</h1>

<p>Looking forward to to this year, we&rsquo;re excited to be working on lots of new projects, with new
partners, as well as continuing to develop and improve our existing services.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve got a project you think we could help with this year, do drop us a line at
<a href="mailto:hello@openhealthcare.org.uk"><a href="&#x6d;&#x61;&#x69;&#x6c;&#116;&#111;&#58;&#104;&#x65;&#108;&#x6c;&#x6f;&#x40;&#x6f;&#112;&#x65;&#x6e;&#x68;&#101;&#97;&#x6c;&#x74;&#x68;&#x63;&#x61;&#114;&#x65;&#46;&#x6f;&#114;&#103;&#46;&#x75;&#107;">&#x68;&#101;&#108;&#108;&#111;&#x40;&#111;&#x70;&#x65;&#x6e;&#104;&#x65;&#97;&#108;&#116;&#104;&#99;&#97;&#x72;&#x65;&#x2e;&#x6f;&#114;&#103;&#x2e;&#x75;&#107;</a></a> - we&rsquo;d love to
hear all about it!</p>

<p><small>
Photo credits: <a href="https://secure.flickr.com/photos/paul_clarke/">Paul Clarke</a>
</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OPAL 0.5 Released]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/11/13/opal-05-released/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-13T16:00:55+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/11/13/opal-05-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We&rsquo;re happy to announce that we&rsquo;ve just released a new version of <a href="http://opal.openhealthcare.org.uk/docs/">OPAL</a> -
our framework for building clinical facing digital services.</p>

<p>So - what&rsquo;s new in this release?</p>

<h2>Search</h2>

<p>We&rsquo;ve completely re-designed our search pages to help clinicians find
the patients they&rsquo;re interested in more easily. We also default to
having a search box in the navigation of every page.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/openhealthcare/openhealthcare.org.uk/master/source/assets/images/posts/search.results.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>In addition, we&rsquo;ve been working hard to make search backends pluggable,
so that in the future you&rsquo;ll be able to drop in alternative backends of
your choice as your application scales.</p>

<h2>Patient List view</h2>

<p>We spent a lot of time over the past few months collating feedback from users and
doing research to understand how we could improve the core Patient List
views. As a response to that we&rsquo;ve updated the list interface - making it clearer
which patient is currently active, and removing some of the features that weren&rsquo;t
actually helping our users to care for patients.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/openhealthcare/openhealthcare.org.uk/master/source/assets/images/posts/list.view.png" alt="" /></p>

<h2>Subrecord metadata</h2>

<p>We added four new utility fields to
<a href="http://opal.openhealthcare.org.uk/docs/guides/datamodel/">Patient and Episode subrecords</a>
 - created_by, updated_by, created, updated. This gives developers easier
programatic access to high level audit trail information, without having
to navigate the <a href="https://github.com/etianen/django-reversion/blob/master/docs/api.rst">low level Django Reversion
API</a>
- which is still there for when you need more detailed audit trail
information.</p>

<h2>Select2 and List fields</h2>

<p>This release introduces
<a href="https://github.com/angular-ui/ui-select">Select2</a> to OPAL - which
provides us some nicer widgets - particularly for fields associated with
<a href="http://opal.openhealthcare.org.uk/docs/guides/lookup_lists/">lookuplists</a>,
and has also enabled the development of list types as
Subrecord fields. For example this means that your travel can be to a
list of countries when you take a backpacking trip through Southeast
Asia!</p>

<h2>What&rsquo;s Next?</h2>

<p>Just because this release is out, we&rsquo;re not resting on our laurels - in
fact we&rsquo;re already gearing up for the next releases. We&rsquo;re planning to
look at the information architecture of Episode detail views, including
a new Notes view that&rsquo;s currently being tested by some users of the
<a href="http://elcid.openhealthcare.org.uk">elCID</a> project.</p>

<p>We also plan to refactor some of the core data models back into OPAL to provide
them there by default rather than implemented over and over again in
individual applications.</p>

<p>As ever, because OPAL is an Open Governance <a href="http://github.com/openhealthcare/opal">Open Source</a> project, you can
follow our progress over on
<a href="https://waffle.io/openhealthcare/opal-ideas">our public Waffle board</a> where we&rsquo;ll be
organising our work.</p>

<h2>More about OPAL</h2>

<p>If you want to find out more about OPAL or how Open Health Care can help
you to run high quality digital services for doctors in your institution
then do get in touch!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Launching a New Clinical Digital Service for Returning Travellers]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/10/21/launching-a-new-walk-in-service/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-21T21:00:29+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/10/21/launching-a-new-walk-in-service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just a couple of weeks ago we launched a new service at the <a href="http://www.thehtd.org/home.aspx">Hospital for Tropical Diseases</a>
in London to help the doctors and nurses who run their <a href="http://www.thehtd.org/emergencies.aspx">Emergency Walk-In Clinic</a>.
At the clinic,
travellers who have returned from the tropics and are acutely unwell turn up without requiring an appointment to get treated
by specialists in tropical diseases. The service tracks patients on their journey through the clinic, from initial triage to
following up on lab results that arrive after they&rsquo;ve left.</p>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/walkin.referral.png" alt="" style="border: 2px solid black;" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->


<p>We worked closely with the staff who run the clinic, making sure that we met the different needs of different types of user
- in this case admin staff, the nursing staff, doctors, as well as the service managers who wanted data on what activity was
happening. Just like we do with all of our services, we brought them into our agile development process as we iteratively
developed the service based on research and their feedback.</p>

<p>Clinical digital services too often fail to take into account the experiences of the people on the ground who have to use
them in practice. At Open Health Care we don&rsquo;t think that&rsquo;s acceptable for something as important as delivering health care.</p>

<p>Because of that we will continue to regularly meet with users of the service to conduct usability testing and actively seek
feedback so that we can continuously improve the service. That feedback loop needs to be a part of the ongoing operation of
digital products and services in hospitals - not just something that happens as part of an initial design phase - and we&rsquo;ve
seen before just how useful it can be as we&rsquo;ve been able to respond to changing user needs and changes to the context and
processes that surround users experiences of our services.</p>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/walkin.nurseledcare.png" alt="" style="border: 2px solid black;" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->




<h2>Use data to design services.<br>It makes things better</h2>


<p>One of the key goals of the project was to allow the team at HTD to gather high quality data about the cohort of patients
that they treat. This data is hugely valuable, both academically for research purposes, and because it enables the team
to understand their workload.</p>

<p>When the tools that are used for routine day-to-day clinical care don&rsquo;t collect usable data, the cost of analysing what you&rsquo;ve
been doing become huge. With the new Walk-in service however, all of the information that the institution knows about a patient,
from demographics to observations, travel history to treatment, gets stored as high quality structured data.</p>

<p>That means that anyone can get an accurate answer to a question like &ldquo;How many patients did we see with Dengue fever in the last
year&rdquo; in seconds, rather than it taking hours or days of painstaking work reviewing case notes, or manually curating and maintaining
their own databases.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re excited about the possibilities for service redesign and research that this new capability has opened up for the team, and
we&rsquo;ve already been brainstorming ideas - so watch this space!</p>

<h2>How it all came together</h2>

<p>The service was built as a <a href="https://github.com/openhealthcare/opal-walk-in">plugin</a> for <a href="http://opal.openhealthcare.org.uk">OPAL</a> -
our open source framework for building high quality digital services in a clinical setting, and is deployed as part of
<a href="http://elcid.openhealthcare.org.uk">elCID - an existing service that we run for UCLH</a> to manage patients with infection.</p>

<p>We love delivering high quality digital services for doctors.
If you&rsquo;d like to explore how we might be able to help you out at your
institution, <a href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/contact.html">get in touch</a> - we&rsquo;re always keen to meet people with interesting problems
to solve as we try and make sure that the digital services that clinical staff in the NHS use in their day jobs is as good as the
services they use in their personal lives.</p>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/walkin.advice.png" alt="" style="border: 2px solid black;" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Come Join Us at UK Health Camp !]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/08/10/come-join-us-at-ukhealthcamp/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-10T10:42:20+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/08/10/come-join-us-at-ukhealthcamp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://ukhealthcamp.com/">UK Health Camp</a> - it&rsquo;s happening.</p>

<p>Some great things have happened to digital in the NHS over the last few years - and we&rsquo;re excited to have
played a part in it. We&rsquo;ve seen a wonderful community blossom around <a href="http://nhshackday.com/">NHS Hack Day</a>
- catalysed by their desire to make NHS IT less bad. We&rsquo;ve seen high quality, user needs focussed,
<a href="https://github.com/openhealthcare">open source</a> clinical facing <a href="http://elcid.openhealthcare.org.uk/">digital services</a>
launch in an increasing number of NHS trusts. We&rsquo;ve seen open data used to
demonstrate <a href="http://www.prescribinganalytics.com/">huge potential cost savings</a> to the NHS - helping to reinforce the
commitment to transparency and openness throughout the system.</p>

<p>And those are just the pieces that we&rsquo;ve been involved with - there are so many more happening all through the NHS.</p>

<p>One of the great strengths of the NHS is its decentralization - although it&rsquo;s a public sector institution, much
decision making is devolved to a local level - which means that you see pockets of innovation springing up all around
the country as its remarkable staff strive to deliver better services to patients. The downside of decentralization is
that sometimes those innovations and best practices don&rsquo;t spread as quickly as we&rsquo;d like - which is how we end up with
variation in services.</p>

<p>We believe that local excellence is not good enough - we need scalable excellence if we&rsquo;re to deliver digital services
in health care that are fit for purpose in the twenty first century.</p>

<p>Which is why we&rsquo;ve been working with a super team of friends from across the health system to create a space to help
connect people doing great work in this space with people who understand that we need to do better, faster, wider. A
space to connect, share ideas and make things happen.</p>

<p>That space is <a href="http://ukhealthcamp.com/">UK Health Camp</a>.</p>

<p>UK Health Camp is a free unconference for everyone interested in digital, design, technology and data for health and
care. It&rsquo;s happening in London on the 28th November, and it&rsquo;s going to be the most exciting conversation around for
people who want to understand how we can deliver better services to patients by using better digital, better data and
better design.</p>

<p>We haven&rsquo;t released tickets just yet, but we expect them to go fast when we do release them - so sign up to the mailing
list to get notified when they do become available.</p>

<p>We look forward to seeing you there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing NHS Hack Day 11 - Manchester!]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/07/08/announcing-nhs-hack-day-11/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-08T21:42:20+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/07/08/announcing-nhs-hack-day-11</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We&rsquo;re delighted to announce that NHS Hack Day is coming to Manchester on the 12-13 September. This is the first time we&rsquo;ve taken the event
to Manchester, and we&rsquo;re all very excited to be doing so with the help of the super <a href="http://twitter.com/marcus_baw">Marcus Baw</a>!</p>

<p><a href="http://nhshackday.com">NHS Hack Days</a> are weekend events that bring together &ldquo;geeks who love the NHS&rdquo; to have fun, build community, and work on digital projects that promote health.</p>

<p>The format is that we begin on a saturday morning with people pitching real-world problems they’ve encountered in the NHS or in health care generally. Anyone can pitch. We end on Sunday afternoon with a competition for the best solutions made over the weekend. In between people pick projects to work on, work on them, and have lunch (provided).</p>

<p>Previous NHS Hack Days have looked something like this:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3NnfMmKKvBk" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Do check out some of the <a href="http://nhshackday.com/previous/projects/">projects that have come fom the event</a> and
read our summary of the <a href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/05/25/nhs-hack-day-10/">previous NHS Hack Day</a></p>

<h3>Why should I come to NHS Hack Day?</h3>

<p>You’ll meet bright people from different disciplines you wouldn’t usually meet
You’ll play a part in making NHS IT less bad
You’ll have fun</p>

<p>We especially want people who aren’t sure if this is for them to come, a lot of the value of the event comes from the diversity of the participants, we need you!
<a href="http://nhshackday.com/faqs/#inclusivity">Imposters are welcome</a></p>

<h3>How do I get involved?</h3>

<ul>
<li>By attending the event, tickets will be released this evening from <a href="http://nhshackday.com">www.nhshackday.com</a></li>
<li>By sponsoring the event - email <a href="&#109;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#x74;&#x6f;&#x3a;&#x68;&#x65;&#108;&#x6c;&#x6f;&#x40;&#111;&#112;&#101;&#110;&#104;&#101;&#x61;&#x6c;&#116;&#104;&#x63;&#97;&#114;&#x65;&#x2e;&#x6f;&#x72;&#x67;&#x2e;&#x75;&#x6b;">&#104;&#101;&#108;&#x6c;&#111;&#x40;&#x6f;&#x70;&#x65;&#110;&#x68;&#x65;&#97;&#108;&#x74;&#104;&#x63;&#x61;&#x72;&#101;&#46;&#x6f;&#114;&#103;&#46;&#x75;&#x6b;</a></li>
<li>By becoming part of our community - joining the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/nhshackday">mailing list</a>, coming to pre event meet ups or talking to us on <a href="http://twitter.com/nhshackday">Twitter</a></li>
<li>By spreading the word, tell your friends!</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Run a Hack Day]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/06/18/how-to-run-a-hackday/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-18T09:00:29+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/06/18/how-to-run-a-hackday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><i>This post is the prose form of a workshop we recently ran at the <a href="https://twitter.com/bisgovuk">Department for Business, Innovation and Skills</a>
about hack days.</i></p>

<p>So, you want to run a hack day?</p>

<blockquote class="custom-quote"><p><i class="fa fa-quote-left"></i>
A hack day is an event in which domain experts with user needs collaborate with people who have skills in delivering digital 
products and services including developers, designers, user researchers and product specialists. 
Hack days typically last between a day and a week. Some hack days are intended simply for educational or social purposes, 
although in many cases the goal is to create usable software.
</p></blockquote>


<p>Hack days are a great way to get multidisciplinary teams working together to create creative tangible solutions to real
world problems.</p>

<h3>Why are you doing this?</h3>

<p>The first thing you&rsquo;ll need to figure out is <em>why</em> you&rsquo;re running a hack day.</p>

<p>There are broadly five reasons people run hack days.</p>

<ol>
<li>To build community</li>
<li>To educate people</li>
<li>To get focussed fast paced R&amp;D</li>
<li>For PR</li>
<li>er hack days are cool, what do you mean why?</li>
</ol>


<p>You should make sure you have a clear answer to <em>why</em> you&rsquo;re doing this before you start running a hack day - because this maximises the likelihood
that you and your attendees will have a great time and get lots of value from the event.</p>

<p>For instance, with <a href="http://nhshackday.com">NHS Hack Day</a> - the events that we run around the country for &ldquo;Geeks who love the NHS&rdquo; - we have a few
reasons. We&rsquo;re aiming to:</p>

<ol>
<li>Build community and friendships between members of the clinical and technology sectors</li>
<li>Show front line clinical staff just how good Digital Services can be, empowering them to demand better from their institutions when they go back to work</li>
<li>Showcase Open Source, Open Governance, and the power of collaborating in small heterogeneous teams of domain experts.</li>
</ol>


<p>That&rsquo;s reasons 1, 2 and a little bit of 4.</p>

<p>You might be looking to build the cross-disciplinary skills of your teams, introducing people to Digital ways of working, thinking and approaching
problems, you might be looking to provide concrete examples of products and services aligned with your policy goals - understanding that showing is more
powerful than telling. Whatever your reason is, make sure you can explain it clearly so that you remain focussed on that throughout.</p>

<h3>What do you need to do?</h3>

<p>So, you want to run a hack day ?</p>

<p>Great!</p>

<p>There are <a href="http://hackdaymanifesto.com/">lots</a> <a href="https://hackathon.guide/">of</a> <a href="http://nhshackday.com/tools/organiser-notes/">documents</a> out there that
will take you through the low level details, we&rsquo;re not going to go through those again in detail, but you basically need to put five things in a room:</p>

<ol>
<li>User needs</li>
<li>Wifi</li>
<li>Power</li>
<li>Coffee</li>
<li>Technologists who know how to deliver Digital</li>
</ol>


<h3>Start with needs</h3>

<p>The value that comes from the event is directly related to the quality of the ideas for projects that are in the room. The <em>best</em> hack day projects
address specific real world user needs. It&rsquo;s well worth thinking about these before the event, and seeking feedback from others - particularly from
people who&rsquo;ve attended hack days before.</p>

<p>With NHS Hack Day, we encourage people to discuss their ideas on our mailing list, on Twitter, and in person
at meetups so that we can help people come with well formed ideas that inspire our attendees. For more focussed commercial hack days we work with
people to frame and present their ideas in such a way that they work well within the context of a hack day.</p>

<h3>Basic logistics</h3>

<p>Hack days have some slightly special logistical requirements of the room that you&rsquo;re going to be in. The most frequent problem is that the Wifi isn&rsquo;t
good enough. As the <a href="http://hackdaymanifesto.com/">Hack Day Manifesto</a> says:</p>

<blockquote class="custom-quote"><p><i class="fa fa-quote-left"></i>
Don’t just trust anyone who tells you that “it’ll be fine”. People from the venue or their commercial partner will tell you all sorts of things you 
want to hear but keep in the back of your mind that they may not have any clue what they are talking about.
</p></blockquote>


<p>In addition to this, you&rsquo;ll also have lots of people wanting to plug in their laptops, so try to make sure that there is good access to power points.
Providing tea, coffee and other beverages as well as lunch and breakfast is always appreciated by attendees, as are easily accessible whiteboards,
flip charts, post-its &amp; sharpies.</p>

<h3>Making your ideas a reality</h3>

<p>At the end of your hack day, you&rsquo;ll have a wrap up session where everyone presents what they&rsquo;ve been working on. There will be lots of excitement and
energy in the room, you may even have judges and prizes! If all has gone well, several prototypes of new Digital products or services will exist that
didn&rsquo;t at the start of the day.</p>

<p>If your aim was to build community and educate people, then you should already have gone a long way to meeting your goals! Sometimes though, you will
want to find a way to take promising projects forwards and make them genuine products or services.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re looking to do this, then it&rsquo;s worth thinking about that path before the event. This might involve providing investment or support for teams
who want to go forward with their idea, promising people time to work on their project, or giving projects marketing and promotion. The details are
often dependent on who you are, and what kinds of user needs you&rsquo;re looking to meet.</p>

<h3>Still want some more help?</h3>

<p>If you&rsquo;re still unsure about how to run your hack day, Open Health Care UK provide strategic and logistical support to organisations in healthcare and
the wider public sector looking to run great events - so drop us a line at <a href="hello@openhealthcare.org.uk">hello@openhealthcare.org.uk</a> to see how we
can help.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[elCID in the Journal of Infection]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/06/10/elcid-journal-of-infectioncontrol/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-10T21:00:29+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/06/10/elcid-journal-of-infectioncontrol</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the past couple of years, Open Health Care has been working in collaboration
with <a href="https://www.uclh.nhs.uk/Pages/home.aspx">UCLH</a> and the <a href="http://www.thehtd.org/">Hospital for Tropical Diseases</a>
on <a href="http://elcid.openhealthcare.org.uk/">elCID</a> (the
electronic Clinical Infection Database) - an Open Source
clinical Digital service for managing inpatients and outpatients with infections.</p>

<p>elCID solves two key clinical problems - first it provides an interface for recording day-to-day
clinical care. We&rsquo;ve developed this interface in close collaboration with clinicians with a strong focus on usability,
using <a href="https://www.gov.uk/service-manual/user-centred-design">user centred design</a> techniques, and
frequent iterations, to make sure that we meet the real needs of our users.</p>

<p>Second, elCID captures structured data about clinical activity, and features advanced
interrogation and extract capabilities. This enables data driven feedback loops in the
design of clinical services, by enabling high quality audits to be conducted much faster
than was ever possible before.</p>

<p>Working with some of the academics who&rsquo;ve been instrumental in developing the
project, we recently published an analysis of the early findings from this process in the
<a href="http://www.journalofinfection.com/article/S0163-4453(15)00100-0/abstract">Journal of Infection</a>.</p>

<p>As the paper outlines:</p>

<blockquote class="custom-quote"><p><i class="fa fa-quote-left"></i>
elCID brings together disparate silos of clinical data collection into a single, rapidly searchable database resource permitting unprecedented interrogation of our clinical practice. <br />
However, the benefits of the system go further, having vastly improved the quality and transparency of communication between the Division’s teams, audits of day-to-day clinical practice are now rapidly and routinely performed using high quality prospectively collected data, and research study data collection can be conducted within the main database, facilitating improved integration of the clinical and academic arms of the Division.
</p></blockquote>


<p>elCID is an Open Source, Open Governance project built on the Open Source <a href="http://opal.openhealthcare.org.uk/">OPAL</a>
framework. It is available to infection services and comes with full support and customisation from Open Health Care.
You can find out more information about the software on the <a href="http://elcid.openhealthcare.org.uk/">elCID website</a>.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re interested in seeing how elCID might help at your organisation, or if you&rsquo;d
like a copy of the full paper, don&rsquo;t hesitate to drop us a line at <a href="hello@openhealthcare.org.uk">hello@openhealthcare.org.uk</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NHS Hack Day 10 - London]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/05/25/nhs-hack-day-10/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-25T16:00:29+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/05/25/nhs-hack-day-10</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend saw us reach a milestone as we brought
<a href="http://nhshackday.com/">NHS Hack Day back to London</a> in our tenth event in just three years!</p>

<p>NHS Hack Days are weekend events that bring together patients, healthcare and technology
professionals and other “geeks who love the NHS” under the banner of making NHS IT less bad.
It&rsquo;s always a pleasure to see so many talented people come together to share their time, skills
and experience to create something together, and this was no exception.</p>

<p>The event started with clinical staff, patients, and anyone else who felt they had a way to
make the world a little better pitching ideas that they wanted to work on. Pitches
<a href="https://www.gov.uk/service-manual/user-centred-design/user-needs.html">start with a User Need</a>
- for instance the surgeons who need a way to track their continuing professional development,
or the doctor who wants quick and easy offline access to formulary information. The attendees
then pick what project they want to work on, and form teams to try and build a prototype over
the weekend.</p>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/nhshd.10.circle.jpg" alt="" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->


<p>At the end of the weekend, we gathered together to share what we&rsquo;d learned and what we&rsquo;d built
over the weekend.</p>

<p>Some of the stand-out projects from the weekend were The Locumator - an app which helps hospital schedulers and doctors to fill vacant slots with bank staff, and Take Your Meds - a low-tech phone reminder application that sends a configurable audio message via phone call to a patient, reminding them to use the mouthwash, or take their medication.</p>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/nhshd.10.chats.jpg" alt="" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->


<p>You can see the whole list <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1-jB5dVPcakZF9HhjXHvqjRtE-vvlkV9NdZ2Qn9II1mc/edit#gid=0">here</a>.</p>

<p>Locumator&rsquo;s presentation</p>

<iframe id="iframe_container" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen="" width="550" height="400" src="https://prezi.com/embed/2hqtpz0eedmg/?bgcolor=ffffff&amp;lock_to_path=0&amp;autoplay=0&amp;autohide_ctrls=0&amp;PARENT_REQUEST_ID=6c9d97d7f3b4b9e3#"></iframe>


<p><br /><br />
More information on Take Your Meds is available from
<a href="https://github.com/open-health-hub/reminder">their Github account</a></p>

<p>This time, our cat-herder in chief was the amazing <a href="http://twitter.com/deckofpandas">@deckofpandas</a> - and we&rsquo;d like to thank her again for all of her hard work in making the event such a great
experience for everyone involved.</p>

<p>Next time looks like being Manchester in Autumn 2015 - although the venue &amp; exact date are
yet to be confirmed. We’d love it if you joined us though - so do
<a href="http://nhshackday.com/">sign up to the mailing list</a> to be kept in the loop !</p>

<p><small>
Photo credits: <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/133318877@N06/">Cléon Daniel</a>
</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Is the Most Cited Retracted Paper?]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/04/16/which-retracted-paper-has-the-most-citations/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-16T16:11:56+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/04/16/which-retracted-paper-has-the-most-citations</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At Open Health Care we believe in
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evidence-based_medicine">Evidence Based Medicine</a>.</p>

<p>Which is why we create digital health <a href="https://github.com/openhealthcare/opal-research">services that support research</a>.</p>

<p>Unfortunately the current infrastructure supporting evidence based medicine has some shortcomings. One of these is that
when a research paper is retracted because, for example, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hwang_Woo-suk">the author</a>
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scientific_misconduct">made up the results</a>, there is little or no means
to propogate this update in the wider medical literature.</p>

<p>Supposing, as a doctor, I look to a systematic review on the management of heart attacks to inform how I treat my patient,
I sadly have no assurance that the systematic review does not rely on research papers that have been retracted. This is suboptimal.</p>

<p>Open access, post-publication peer review, and better version control would be three useful features that a modern scientific
publishing model optimized to enable good science should support.</p>

<p>In the meantime, inspired by a lunchtime conversation with our friend and director Ben Goldacre (it was all his idea),
we pondered the question:</p>

<blockquote class="custom-quote"><p><i class="fa fa-question fa-3x"></i>
What is the most cited retracted paper?
</p></blockquote>


<p>It turns out <a href="http://www.pubmed.gov">PubMed</a> already has a nice API that can return a
<a href="http://eutils.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/eutils/esearch.fcgi?db=pubmed&amp;retmode=json&amp;retmax=10000&amp;term=%22retracted%20publication%22">list</a>
of PubMed ids for papers that have been retracted. Next we needed a means of knowing how many times each retracted paper was cited.
There are a few ways of doing this but we went with using google scholar after Alf Eaton told us about it on
<a href="https://twitter.com/invisiblecomma/status/582904870644113408">twitter</a>. It&rsquo;s possible to search google scholar for the articles
citing a particular pubmed id, here&rsquo;s an <a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar?cites=http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19336536">example</a>.</p>

<p>Finally, we used wget to download all of the google scholar search results.  This infamous
<a href="http://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736%2897%2911096-0/abstract">paper</a> &lsquo;Ileal-lymphoid-nodular hyperplasia,
non-specific colitis, and pervasive developmental disorder in children.&rsquo; was the winner with
2070 <a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar?cites=http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9500320">citations</a>!</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the top ten:</p>

<table class="table table-striped">
<tbody><tr><td>Citations</td>
<td colspan="2">Title</td>
<td>Author</td>
<td>Journal</td>
<td>Pubdate</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>2070</td>
<td colspan="2"><a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar?cites=http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9500320">
Ileal-lymphoid-nodular hyperplasia, non-specific colitis, and pervasive developmental disorder in children.
</a>
</td>
<td>Wakefield AJ</td>
<td>Lancet</td>
<td>28/02/1998</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>2050</td>
<td colspan="2">
<a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar?cites=http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15604363">
Visfatin: a protein secreted by visceral fat that mimics the effects of insulin.
</a>
</td>
<td>Fukuhara A</td>
<td>Science (New York, N.Y.)</td>
<td>21/01/2005</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>1550</td>
<td colspan="2">
<a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar?cites=http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11675329">
Purification and ex vivo expansion of postnatal human marrow mesodermal progenitor cells.
</a>
</td>
<td>Reyes M</td>
<td>Blood</td>
<td>01/11/2001</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>1250</td>
<td colspan="2">
<a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar?cites=http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12531578">
Combination treatment of angiotensin-II receptor blocker and angiotensin-converting-enzyme inhibitor in non-diabetic renal disease (COOPERATE): a randomised controlled trial.
</a>
</td>
<td>Nakao N</td>
<td>Lancet</td>
<td>11/01/2003</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>1040</td>
<td colspan="2">
<a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar?cites=http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15833829">
Spontaneous human adult stem cell transformation.
</a>
</td>
<td>Rubio D</td>
<td>Cancer research</td>
<td>15/04/2005</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>825</td>
<td colspan="2">
<a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar?cites=http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/10700237">
Regression of human metastatic renal cell carcinoma after vaccination with tumor cell-dendritic cell hybrids.
</a>
</td>
<td>Kugler A</td>
<td>Nature medicine</td>
<td>01/03/2000</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>805</td>
<td colspan="2">
<a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar?cites=http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/14963337">
Evidence of a pluripotent human embryonic stem cell line derived from a cloned blastocyst.
</a>
</td>
<td>Hwang WS</td>
<td>Science (New York, N.Y.)</td>
<td>12/03/2004</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>755</td>
<td colspan="2">
<a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar?cites=http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12176951">
Multiple atherosclerotic plaque rupture in acute coronary syndrome: a three-vessel intravascular ultrasound study.
</a>
</td>
<td>Rioufol G</td>
<td>Circulation</td>
<td>13/08/2002</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>732</td>
<td colspan="2">
<a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar?cites=http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/11546864">
Structure of MsbA from E. coli: a homolog of the multidrug resistance ATP binding cassette (ABC) transporters.
<a/>
</td>
<td>Chang G</td>
<td>Science (New York, N.Y.)</td>
<td>07/09/2001</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>616</td>
<td colspan="2">
<a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar?cites=http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/8633243">
Synergistic activation of estrogen receptor with combinations of environmental chemicals.
</a>
</td>
<td>Arnold SF</td>
<td>Science (New York, N.Y.)</td>
<td>07/06/1996</td>
</tr>
<tr><td>607</td>
<td colspan="2">
<a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar?cites=http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/12351674">
Contribution of human alpha-defensin 1, 2, and 3 to the anti-HIV-1 activity of CD8 antiviral factor.
</a>
</td>
<td>Zhang L</td>
<td>Science (New York, N.Y.)</td>
<td>01/11/2002</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table>


<p>You can reproduce our results or view our workings <a href="https://github.com/drcjar/retractshons">over on Github</a>.</p>

<p>There are of course many reasons other than the author making up the results for a paper to be retracted. There are also many circumstances
in which citing a retracted paper is legitimate. For a more nuanced discussion of retractions there&rsquo;s a nice <a href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0044118">Comprehensive Survey of
Retracted Articles from the Scholarly Literature</a> in PLOS and the
excellent <a href="http://retractionwatch.com/">Retraction Watch</a> covers the details of individual retractions as they happen.</p>

<p>Anyway, it was fun to examine retractions. We&rsquo;d love to explore this further so if we can be of service to you do get in touch.</p>

<p>Perhaps a project for <a href="http://www.nhshackday.com">NHS Hack Day</a>?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[London NHS Hack Day Meet Up]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/04/01/london-nhs-hack-day-meet-up/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-01T11:39:55+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/04/01/london-nhs-hack-day-meet-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Calling all friends of <a href="http://nhshackday.com">NHS Hack Day</a>:</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re<a href="https://attending.io/events/nhshd-10-meetup-times"> having a meet up</a> on Thursday 16 April, and we&rsquo;d love to see you there !</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re going to be in the George Inn near London Bridge from 18:00, and
we&rsquo;d love to talk to people about not just the
<a href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/03/17/nhs-hack-day-10/">upcoming NHS Hack day</a>,
but also any of the other ways that technology and data can make the NHS better,
make new friends, &amp; even start planning how to make some of those ideas a reality!</p>

<p><b>Where:</b> <a href="https://attending.io/events/nhshd-10-meetup-times#map">The George Inn</a></p>

<p><b>When:</b>  Thu 16 April 2015 18:00-21:00</p>

<p><b>Who:</b> Anyone &amp; everyone ! All welcome, no specialist skills or knowledge required&hellip;</p>

<p><b>How:</b> Just turning up is fine, but you can also add yourself to our <a href="https://attending.io/events/nhshd-10-meetup-times">event page</a>.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re thinking of attending NHS Hack day, have a good NHS related problem that you want to
see solved, or are just curious as to what all this is about, this is
a great event for you! We&rsquo;ll have the <a href="http://twitter.com/nhshackday">@NHSHackDay</a> team on
hand, and we&rsquo;re excited to hear your great ideas ahead of the event next month!</p>

<p><small>
Photo credits: <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/andrewasmith/">Andrew Smith</a>
</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[It's Time for NHS Hack Day 10]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/03/17/nhs-hack-day-10/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-17T20:42:20+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/03/17/nhs-hack-day-10</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://nhshackday.com">NHS Hack Days</a> are weekend events that bring together &ldquo;geeks who love the NHS&rdquo; to have fun, build community, and work on digital projects that promote health.</p>

<p>NHS Hack Day began in 2012 when Carl (a doctor) complained to his friend Tom (a developer) that things were really very broken in NHS IT. Tom who’d recently had a good experience at a Cabinet Office GDS Hack Day said the NHS should have a hack day. So we did.</p>

<p>The format is that we begin on a saturday morning with people pitching real-world problems they’ve encountered in the NHS or in health care generally. Anyone can pitch. We end on Sunday afternoon with a competition for the best solutions made over the weekend. In between people pick projects to work on, work on them, and have lunch (provided).</p>

<p>Previous NHS Hack Days have looked something like this:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3NnfMmKKvBk" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Do check out some of the <a href="http://nhshackday.com/previous/projects/">projects that have come fom the event</a> and
read our summary of the <a href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/01/31/nhs-hack-day-cardiff/">previous NHS Hack Day</a></p>

<h3>Why should I come to NHS Hack Day?</h3>

<p>You’ll meet bright people from different disciplines you wouldn’t usually meet
You’ll play a part in making NHS IT less bad
You’ll have fun</p>

<p>We especially want people who aren’t sure if this is for them to come, a lot of the value of the event comes from the diversity of the participants, we need you!
<a href="http://nhshackday.com/faqs/#inclusivity">Imposters are welcome</a></p>

<h3>How do I get involved?</h3>

<ul>
<li>By attending the event, tickets will be released this evening from <a href="http://nhshackday.com">www.nhshackday.com</a></li>
<li>By sponsoring the event - email <a href="&#x6d;&#x61;&#105;&#x6c;&#116;&#x6f;&#x3a;&#x68;&#x65;&#108;&#x6c;&#x6f;&#64;&#x6f;&#112;&#x65;&#x6e;&#104;&#101;&#97;&#108;&#116;&#x68;&#x63;&#97;&#114;&#x65;&#46;&#111;&#x72;&#x67;&#x2e;&#117;&#107;">&#x68;&#101;&#x6c;&#108;&#111;&#x40;&#x6f;&#x70;&#101;&#x6e;&#104;&#101;&#97;&#x6c;&#116;&#104;&#x63;&#x61;&#114;&#x65;&#46;&#x6f;&#x72;&#x67;&#x2e;&#x75;&#107;</a></li>
<li>By becoming part of our community - joining the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/nhshackday">mailing list</a>, coming to pre event meet ups or talking to us on <a href="http://twitter.com/nhshackday">Twitter</a></li>
<li>By spreading the word, tell your friends!</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Open Politics]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/03/12/open-politics/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-12T15:42:20+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/03/12/open-politics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><i>This is a guest post by <a href="http://ntoll.org">Nicholas Tollervey</a></i></p>

<p>The purpose of this post is to explore openness in government
technology. I&rsquo;ve been asked to advise on this subject for
<a href="http://www.england.nhs.uk/">NHS England</a>.
I shall be directing the civil servants I have been working with to this
article.</p>

<p>To many people much of this post will be old news. Unfortunately
we are in the minority. Hence the need for this summary.</p>

<p>As always, feedback and comments are most welcome; in fact, comments
will be quite useful given the readership will include civil
servants who can make changes within NHS England. Think of it as an
unofficial opportunity for engagement with the unelected arm of the
government.</p>

<p>The moral argument for openness in government is simple: it is a
fundamental requirement for a democratic society. Without the ability to
observe what and how the government is doing, how are citizens to
evaluate politicians come polling day?</p>

<p>Yet openness is too broad a term - in this sense it is perhaps a virtue
of a good political system. Therefore I will simply state three
practical embodiments of the virtue of openness:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Open data</strong> - data should be freely available without restrictions of
copyright, patents or other controls;</li>
<li><strong>Open media</strong> - data generated by the government should be in a format
that is accessible to everyone;</li>
<li><strong>Open processes</strong> - what the government does should be transparent,
recorded and accountable.</li>
</ol>


<p>The UK Government has been
<a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/open-data-white-paper-unleashing-the-potential">vocal in the promotion of open data</a>
(point 1). Yet it is not good enough to simply publish data. The format
and structure of the data is critical (point 2), as is its provenance
(point 3).</p>

<p>Regarding point 2: what&rsquo;s the point of publishing data if there&rsquo;s no way
for people to make use of it? After all, when data is read, analysed and
interpreted it becomes useful information. Publishing data in a medium
that only works with a single piece of software (such as releasing
tabular data that can only be read by Excel) makes it frustratingly
difficult use. While I welcome the publication of data I&rsquo;d much
rather it were in a friendly open format (such as <a href="http://data.okfn.org/doc/csv">releasing tabular data
as a CSV</a>).</p>

<p>Regarding point 3: what&rsquo;s the point of publishing data if there&rsquo;s no way
to  discover how it was compiled, by whom and with what intention? It
should be possible to independently check the reports published by
government through access to the raw data and (crucially) the
algorithms, processes and pipelines used to aggregate, transform and
generate the end result. Furthermore, an open process allows people to
examine, test and improve the methodology involved in generating data.
It will no longer be the case that compiling some-report-or-other is
only understood by a couple of government statisticians - this essential
organisational information would be available to all.</p>

<p>While this sounds like an onerous task for civil servants it is
important to note that these three practices actually make life easier
for all involved, including civil servants.</p>

<p>From a technical point of view, it&rsquo;s impossible to work effectively in
digital walled gardens where opaque solutions don&rsquo;t quite work
properly and are too expensive to migrate away from. Open standards
allow anyone (including civil servants) the flexibility to use their own
choice of tool for the job in hand as illustrated by the diagram
below.</p>

<p><img
src="https://assets.digital.cabinet-office.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/image_data/file/8854/open_formats_standards_960x640.png"/></p>

<p>As the Cabinet Office minister <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/open-standards-principles/open-standards-principles">Francis Maud states</a>,</p>

<blockquote class="custom-quote"><p><i class="fa fa-quote-left"></i>

Government IT must be open - open to the people and organisations that
use our services and open to any provider, regardless of their size.
<br />
We currently have many small, separate platforms operating across
disconnected departments and IT that is tied into monolithic contracts.
We need to have a platform for government that allows us to share
appropriate data effectively and that gives us flexibility and choice.
</p></blockquote>


<p>Contrast this vision with the incumbant alternative (based on real life
experiences working with statisticians within NHS England):</p>

<ul>
<li><p>No-one wants to work in a world where the data they need
for their report is held within a complex Excel spreadsheet with
meaningless column names generated by a team who never
answers email.</p></li>
<li><p>No-one wants to work with a spreadsheet that is subtly different each
time it gets published causing doubts about its reliability and
provenance.</p></li>
<li><p>No-one wants to work with a spreadsheet hosted on a website created in
2005 where the only way to get at it is to download a Java applet (the
technical equivalent of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ozymandias">ruins of Ozymandias</a>
) and manually press a
button on a computer logged into the very special VPN that never works
when you need it to.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Such a chain of opaque technology comes at great cost in terms of
time, efficiency and job satisfaction. Highly trained NHS
statisticians do not enjoy spending hours downloading, revising,
copying, pasting and re-uploading shonky spreadsheets.</p>

<p>They want to <strong>work with data</strong>, not push it around.</p>

<p>They want to <strong>access the data</strong>, not spend hours clicking buttons.</p>

<p>They want to <strong>understand</strong> their colleagues&#8217; work and know who to contact
if there&rsquo;s a problem.</p>

<p><img src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/hope.jpg" /></p>

<p>Happily, there are signs of hope.</p>

<p>In the first instance civil servants should be following the
<a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/open-standards-principles/open-standards-principles">Open Standards Principles</a>
from the Cabinet Office</p>

<p>It is a simple and easy to understand guide for using open
standards in government. If you&rsquo;re a civil servant working with data
you should be following this checklist:</p>

<ol>
<li>We place the needs of our users at the heart of our standards choices</li>
<li>Our selected open standards will enable suppliers to compete on alevel playing field</li>
<li>Our standards choices support flexibility and change</li>
<li>We adopt open standards that support sustainable cost</li>
<li>Our decisions about standards selection are well informed</li>
<li>We select open standards using fair and transparent processes</li>
<li>We are fair and transparent in the specification and implementation of open standards</li>
</ol>


<p>It is no longer acceptable to say things like, &ldquo;but the needs of our
legacy system mean you should use &lt;closed technology X&gt;&rdquo;. If you hear
such a remark, point the perpetrator at the checklist above. If they
claim it would be too expensive to migrate, explain that it&rsquo;s because it
is so expensive to migrate that such a system needs changing (such
expense only ever grows over time, change things sooner rather than
later). If they assert that it&rsquo;s not organisational policy to use
open process Y ask them to justify themselves within the framework
described in the policy document above (that became active on 1st
November 2012). Cabinet Office advice when
<a href="https://www.gov.uk/service-manual/making-software/choosing-technology.html">choosing technologies</a>
is that one should express requirements in terms of user needs and capabilities
not incumbent institutional needs. Furthermore, when considering the choice
of technology, they state,</p>

<blockquote class="custom-quote"><p><i class="fa fa-quote-left"></i>
All things being equal, picking technologies that developers and operations staff like will typically result in improved productivity.
</blockquote>


<p>A second positive is that there appear to be politicians of all
affiliations who understand and have the political will to promote open
standards.</p>

<p>Consider the following exchange between myself and Meg Hillier MP:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p>.<a href="https://twitter.com/Meg_HillierMP">@Meg_HillierMP</a>, given ubiquity of closed formats (MS Office etc), will Parliament switch to publish w/open data formats? <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/digitaldemocracy?src=hash">#digitaldemocracy</a></p>&mdash; Nicholas Tollervey (@ntoll) <a href="https://twitter.com/ntoll/status/575253094663122944">March 10, 2015</a></blockquote>




<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" lang="en"><p>.<a href="https://twitter.com/ntoll">@ntoll</a> yes..that&#39;s the plan. New head of Parliament Digital Service <a href="https://twitter.com/Rob_Greig">@Rob_Greig</a> is already working on this</p>&mdash; MegHillierMP (@Meg_HillierMP) <a href="https://twitter.com/Meg_HillierMP/status/575258270706892800">March 10, 2015</a></blockquote>




<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p>.<a href="https://twitter.com/Meg_HillierMP">@Meg_HillierMP</a> motivation for my q is current work w/<a href="https://twitter.com/NHSEngland">@NHSEngland</a> stats / data in messy, non-machine readable Excel spreadsheets &amp; PDFs. :-(</p>&mdash; Nicholas Tollervey (@ntoll) <a href="https://twitter.com/ntoll/status/575257864454995969">March 10, 2015</a></blockquote>




<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" lang="en"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/ntoll">@ntoll</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/Meg_HillierMP">@Meg_HillierMP</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/NHSEngland">@NHSEngland</a> &quot;non-machine readable Excel spreadsheets&quot; &#8211;&gt; cold shiver in my spine</p>&mdash; Giovanni Idili (@John_Idol) <a href="https://twitter.com/John_Idol/status/575261025395720192">March 10, 2015</a></blockquote>




<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" lang="en"><p>.<a href="https://twitter.com/John_Idol">@John_Idol</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/ntoll">@ntoll</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/NHSEngland">@NHSEngland</a> and that&#39;s not the worst of it! sometimes they are not even readable in paper form</p>&mdash; MegHillierMP (@Meg_HillierMP) <a href="https://twitter.com/Meg_HillierMP/status/575261373304803330">March 10, 2015</a></blockquote>




<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" lang="en"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/Meg_HillierMP">@Meg_HillierMP</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/John_Idol">@John_Idol</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/NHSEngland">@NHSEngland</a> good point - demonstrates accountability/evidence: confusing data=confused understanding perhaps?</p>&mdash; Nicholas Tollervey (@ntoll) <a href="https://twitter.com/ntoll/status/575261775446306817">March 10, 2015</a></blockquote>




<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" lang="en"><p>.<a href="https://twitter.com/ntoll">@ntoll</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/John_Idol">@John_Idol</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/NHSEngland">@NHSEngland</a> yes. We are coming from same place on this issue. Open Up! <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/digitaldemocracy?src=hash">#digitaldemocracy</a></p>&mdash; MegHillierMP (@Meg_HillierMP) <a href="https://twitter.com/Meg_HillierMP/status/575262116405460992">March 10, 2015</a></blockquote>




<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" lang="en"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/Meg_HillierMP">@Meg_HillierMP</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/John_Idol">@John_Idol</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/NHSEngland">@NHSEngland</a> quite&#8230; so having evidence is one thing - but how does a citizen hold publisher accountable?</p>&mdash; Nicholas Tollervey (@ntoll) <a href="https://twitter.com/ntoll/status/575272422582132736">March 10, 2015</a></blockquote>




<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" lang="en"><p>.<a href="https://twitter.com/ntoll">@ntoll</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/John_Idol">@John_Idol</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/NHSEngland">@NHSEngland</a> we need to make it either embarrassing for them or in case of Govt manke it mandatory</p>&mdash; MegHillierMP (@Meg_HillierMP) <a href="https://twitter.com/Meg_HillierMP/status/575301644272996352">March 10, 2015</a></blockquote>




<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>Here&rsquo;s hoping NHS England leads the way in open standards. After all,
they were born from a disparate collection of
existing governmental organisations, each of whom did things differently. Openness is
a way for NHS England to integrate, collaborate and work more effectively towards making
the NHS the world class healthcare system it needs to be.</p>

<p>This is an opportunity that applies to the whole public sector. The cost of inaction would
be to deny the government tools and processes essential for working effectively in a world
in constant flux.</p>

<p>Panta rhei!</p>

<p><small>
Photo credits: <br />
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/opensourceway/">Opensourceway</a><br />
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/polsifter/">Pol Sifter</a>
</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Doctors Get Digital Services They Love]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/03/11/how-doctors-get-digital-services-they-love/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-11T21:12:19+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/03/11/how-doctors-get-digital-services-they-love</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At Open Health Care, we believe in
<a href="https://www.gov.uk/service-manual/user-centred-design">User-centered design</a>.</p>

<p>Which means that we focus on meeting the needs of our users, and is why we
always work in close collaboration with them. Whether that comes in the
form of making sure that our clinical champions are present at every sprint
meeting, or working hard to get clinical staff and patients along to
<a href="http://nhshackday.com">NHS Hack Day</a> we work by putting users first, building
and testing in small chunks.</p>

<p>Working this way means that generally when we work on a project, we identify
clinical champion(s) for that project. These are the kind of people who will use the service
we end up building in their day-to-day work. In order to get them as involved as
possible, we introduce them to <a href="https://www.gov.uk/service-manual/agile">Agile</a>,
and we often find ourselves teaching <a href="https://github.com/GabPoll">doctors</a> to
<a href="https://github.com/michaeledwardmarks">github</a>. (Yes, that&rsquo;s a verb now).</p>

<p>The great thing about working in multidisciplinary teams, is that <em>everyone</em> learns
new things, all the time. For every medical three letter acronym like say,
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Community-acquired_pneumonia">CAP</a> that gets explained
to a developer, there&rsquo;s an explanation of what
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Application_programming_interface">API</a> stands for that goes the
other way.</p>

<p>But it&rsquo;s not just terminology that gets shared - often we try to share our tools. We
promote online
<a href="http://www.google.co.uk/docs/about/">collaborative</a>
<a href="http://hackpad.com/">document</a> editing above email attachments and
<a href="http://thedoghousediaries.com/5964">naming conventions</a>. We encourage users to take
up better web browsers. We get them to try out modern
<a href="https://slack.com/">team communication</a> <a href="http://appear.in">tools</a>, and recommend <a href="http://www.rstudio.com/">Open Source</a>
alternatives to the proprietary default incumbents.</p>

<h3>But wait - it gets better</h3>

<p>Not only does this help us all understand one another better, which is so vital to delivering
high quality digital services, but it also often introduces clinicians to tools that reward
power users with advanced functionality. Once you&rsquo;ve learnt
<a href="https://help.github.com/articles/github-flavored-markdown/">markdown</a> once, typing information
into text boxes that will get rendered in a web browser is never quite the same again. You start
<em>expecting</em> that the web based <a href="http://opal.openhealthcare.org.uk">clinical digital services</a>
you use in your day job let you <a href="https://github.com/openhealthcare/opal/blob/823de649ddee6c13803264d929ece3ae171104c5/opal/static/js/opal/opaldown.js">use markdown</a>
there too.</p>

<p>Possibly the best feature we&rsquo;ve implemented that came about this way is the
<a href="http://opal.openhealthcare.org.uk">OPAL </a>
Macros from
late last year. Directly inspired by <a href="https://github.com/blog/957-introducing-issue-mentions">Github issue mentions</a>,
OPAL Macros let the user define blocks of commonly used text, and then insert them with shortcut Macros -
(names preceded by the # symbol).</p>

<p>For instance, for <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Staphylococcus_aureus">Staph</a> advice, the user enters #st:</p>

<p><img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/features/macro.pre.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>&hellip; which then expands to the (institutionally defined) standard advice for this case:</p>

<p><img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/features/macro.post.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>This is the kind of user need that only even comes up when users are digitally literate enough to
be able to express it - something along the lines of:</p>

<blockquote class="custom-quote"><p><i class="fa fa-user-md fa-3x"></i>
As a Doctor <br />
I want to avoid repeatedly typing out standard advice <br />
So that I can spend more time with my patients
</p></blockquote>


<p>The existence of this kind of power-user functionality encourages users to master their tools, by
offering them time savings and efficiencies but crucially, doesn&rsquo;t interfere with the user experience at all if you
don&rsquo;t know it&rsquo;s there. As
<a href="https://github.com/michaeledwardmarks">Dr Marks</a>, who had originally explained the need on
Github said:</p>

<blockquote class="custom-quote"><p><i class="fa fa-quote-left"></i>
Absolutely stunning.<br/>
I would say this is one of the most incredible things I have seen on a piece of NHS software ever.
</p></blockquote>


<p>If you&rsquo;re interested in starting an OPAL project at your institution to take advantage of this kind
of feature, or in seeing how we can can help you by providing clinical facing digital services,
don&rsquo;t hesitate to <a href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/contact.html">Get in touch</a>!</p>

<p><small>
Photo credits: <br />
<a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/jakuza/">Jacopo Romei</a><br />
</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[elCID OPAT Launched at UCLH]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/02/05/elcid-opat-launch/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-05T09:12:19+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/02/05/elcid-opat-launch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week saw us excited to launch our new <a href="http://e-opat.com/">OPAT</a> (Outpatients
Parenteral Antimicrobial Therapy) service delivered via the <a href="http://elcid.openhealthcare.org.uk">elCID</a>
platform at UCLH.</p>

<p>This is the first deployment of the specialist OPAT module for <a href="http://opal.openhealthcare.org.uk">OPAL</a> -
our Open Source framework for building transactional digital services. It covers the whole range of an
OPAT service - from initial referrals and assessment, through ongoing care, post-treatment follow up and
review. All of the workflows capture high quality data at the time of use, and allow analysis and extraction,
both for reporting in line with national guidelines, and individual service audits.</p>

<p>As ever, we worked closely with clinical champions, who were deeply involved in the agile development process,
weighing in on <a href="https://github.com/openhealthcare/elcid/issues">GitHub</a>, attending sprint meetings, and
providing their expertise to our development team. The whole project is released under an Open Source (GPL)
license, and was developed in the open.</p>

<p>This was a project we loved delivering, and not just because of the high praise from Dr Jon Lambourne, UCLH&rsquo;s
clinical lead on the project, who said:</p>

<blockquote class="custom-quote"><p><i class="fa fa-quote-left"></i>
The Open Health Care team have been super, the things they can get the OPAL software to do regularly leaves me slack-jawed!
</p></blockquote>


<p>While we like to think that we&rsquo;re pretty good at executing on the technology side of things, it&rsquo;s really the collaboration
between us and the clinical users, along with our focus on their needs that makes it possible for us to deliver
new user-focussed digital services into the world.</p>

<p>Accordingly, we&rsquo;d particularly like to thank
<a href="https://www.uclh.nhs.uk/OurServices/Consultants/Pages/DrSarahLogan.aspx">Dr Sarah Logan</a> (Our consultant sponsor),
<a href="https://github.com/7575colli">Steve Collins</a> (OPAT Nurse extraordinaire), and
<a href="https://github.com/jonnylambourne">Dr Jon Lambourne</a> (Clinical lead on the project) for all their efforts.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re interested in seeing an OPAL project at your institution, or in seing how we can can
support running clinical OPAT services, don&rsquo;t hesitate to <a href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/contact.html">Get in touch</a>!</p>

<p><small>
Photo Credits: <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/lydiashiningbrightly/5922822998">Lydia</a>
</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NHS Hack Day 9 - Cardiff]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/01/31/nhs-hack-day-cardiff/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-31T20:02:19+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/01/31/nhs-hack-day-cardiff</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend saw us return to Cardiff for the 9th NHS Hack Day - once again, with organisation
headed up by the life affirming <a href="https://twitter.com/amcunningham">Anne Marie Cunningham</a>.</p>

<p>NHS Hack Days are weekend events that bring together patients, healthcare and technology professionals and other
&ldquo;geeks who love the NHS&rdquo; under the banner of making NHS IT less bad. It&rsquo;s always exciting to see people discover
how digital products are made by &ldquo;Not Magic&rdquo;, not to mention the jaw-dropping that goes on when it gets explained
just how bad much of the status quo really is.</p>

<p>Many of the pitches highlighted the need for quickly and easily customisable hospital systems, that allow
people to collaborate more easily, and also to generate alerts and notifications, routing information that exists
within our institutions to the people who can actually make a difference with it, in time.</p>

<p>As the second day drew to a close, we all gathered together to share what we&rsquo;d made, and what we&rsquo;d learnt over
the weekend.</p>

<p>We thought that the team who rescued <a href="http://virtualmicroscope.readthedocs.org/en/hackday/">Virtual Microscope</a> -
a previously abandonned open source project for viewing, navigating &amp; annotate very high-resolution images deserved
huge credit.</p>

<p>Meanwhile the group that took the Oculus Rift and turned it into an eye-test scenario complete with zombies seemed
like they had a whole world of fun !</p>

<p>In the end the grand prize went to Medboard - a system for connecting medical students to the classes &amp; opportunities
available to them at their respective institutions.</p>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/nhshd9.baby.jpg" alt="" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->


<p>In addition, we were delighted to see our youngest ever attendee to an NHS Hack Day, with Ada Reynolds stealing the record at just
5 weeks old! Although she may have slept through much of this one, we&rsquo;re all looking forward to her contributions next time !</p>

<p>Next time looks like being London in May 2015 - although the venue &amp; exact date are yet to be confirmed. We&rsquo;d love it
if you joined us though - so do <a href="http://nhshackday.com">sign up to the mailing list</a> to be kept in the loop !</p>

<p><small>
Photo credits: <a href="https://secure.flickr.com/photos/paul_clarke/">Paul Clarke</a>
</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2014 - Annual Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/01/19/annual-review/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-19T15:00:29+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/01/19/annual-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>OPAL at UCLH</h3>

<p>Early in the year we deployed <a href="http://elcid.openhealthcare.org.uk">elCID</a> - our custom built digital service for
infection doctors to University College London Hospital.</p>

<p>Despite our early plans for a cautious, staggered rollout, demand from end users to transition to the system meant
that we accelerated rapidly, spreading throughout the division of infection at UCLH and racing through the 1000 patient
mark within the few months.</p>

<p>Not content to sit on our laurels, we&rsquo;ve been further developing the platform, with a specialist OPAT (Outpatients
Parenteral Antimicrobial Therapy) service developed and launched early 2015, and a walk-in clinic service scheduled for
deployment in spring.</p>

<h3>OPAL for research</h3>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/elcid.outputs.png" alt="" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->


<p>2014 saw the first academic outputs from the OPAL project, with two posters presented at the
<a href="http://www.fis-infection.org.uk/">Federation of Infection Societies</a> conference.</p>

<p>Demonstrating the new capabilities for conducting clinical audits and exploring hypotheses about the patient
population treated by UCLH, concluding that:</p>

<pre><code>The electronic prospective data capture benefits of elCID have facilitated organisation
and interrogation of our own clinical practice to greater levels than before, describing 
many hitherto uncaptured elements of clinical activity.
</code></pre>

<h3>Hackdays</h3>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/nhshd6.jpg" alt="" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->


<p>2014 saw the <a href="http:/nhshackday.com">NHS Hack Day</a> train roll in to Cardiff, London and Leeds. As ever
the events saw us take multidisciplinary groups of Doctors, Technologists &amp; Patients for a weekend of
furious hacking, resulting not only in some great new projects, but in hundreds of individual opportunities
for people to connect &amp; learn from each other.</p>

<p>Particularly exciting were <a href="https://github.com/huwlynes/tb_care_plan">TB Care Plan</a> - a single page TB guideline
project that managed to take the rule of &ldquo;As simple as it can possibly be&rdquo; to new heights, and a
<a href="https://github.com/openhealthcare/opal-renal">Renal focussed</a> OPAL implementation for handover and patient management.</p>

<h3>The Future</h3>

<p>2014 has been a great year for Open Health Care, &amp; We&rsquo;re excited looking forward to the year to come !</p>

<p>With new product launches, lots of exciting projects in the pipeline, as well as the relentless programme of running
events up &amp; down the country, we&rsquo;ll be busy!</p>

<p><small>
Photo credits: <a href="https://secure.flickr.com/photos/paul_clarke/">Paul Clarke</a> &amp;&amp; <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/gpollara">Gabriel Pollara</a>
</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
