<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Annualreview | Open Health Care UK - Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/categories/annualreview/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/"/>
  <updated>2019-06-11T11:38:11+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Open Health Care UK]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2015 - Annual Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2016/01/18/annual-review/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-18T15:00:29+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2016/01/18/annual-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>2015 was a big year for us - so we thought we&rsquo;d take a moment and share
some of what we&rsquo;ve been up to:</p>

<h1>Delivering Digital Services for direct care</h1>

<p>We believe that the digital tools used to deliver patient care should be of the highest
possible quality. Not only do we believe it, we work hard to deliver them as well!</p>

<p>Last year we launched two new services - for <a href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/02/05/elcid-opat-launch/">managing OPAT care</a>
at UCLH (patients who need regular IV drugs but aren&rsquo;t so sick that they need to stay in
hospital all the time), and for the returning traveller
<a href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/10/21/launching-a-new-walk-in-service/">walk in clinic</a> at the Hospital for
Tropical Diseases.</p>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/detail.view.png" alt="" style="border: 2px solid black;" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->


<p>We&rsquo;ve also been working to iteratively improve the services we run - conducting user research
interviews, observing clinicians using our tools on the wards, and generally trying to establish
robust feedback loops and processes for users to tell us how we can make things better for them.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">From the wards yesterday: &#10;&#10;&quot;You&#39;re actually coming and asking doctors how you can make the IT systems they use better? - That&#39;s unheard of&quot;</p>&mdash; David Miller (@thatdavidmiller) <a href="https://twitter.com/thatdavidmiller/status/642247781617397760">September 11, 2015</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>Based on this research, we&rsquo;ve made lots of improvements to the UI of our services, coming up
with new design patterns for building applications for direct care in the process.</p>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/list.view.png" alt="" style="border: 2px solid black;" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->


<h1>Code</h1>

<p>Lots of this work invovles us writing, maintaining and improving code.</p>

<p>During 2014 We made 3 major <a href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/11/13/opal-05-released/">new releases</a> of
<a href="http://opal.openhealthcare.org.uk">OPAL</a> - our framework
for building digital services for clnicians, not to mention many other smaller releases,
making up <b>2,416</b> individual commits across all
our <a href="https://github.com/openhealthcare">Open Source projects</a>.</p>

<p>Throughout the year we&rsquo;ve been focussing on making our projects easier for new developers
to pick up - improving the <a href="http://opal.openhealthcare.org.uk/docs">documentation</a> and
refactoring things to provide better APIs for people to build on.</p>

<h1>Hackdays</h1>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/nhshd.10.jpg" alt="" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->


<p>2015 was as busy as ever for <a href="http://nhshackday.com">NHS Hack Day</a>, with three
events bringing together hundreds of clinicians, academics, designers, developers, and
patients to help make the NHS just a little better.</p>

<p>We kicked off the year with another trip to <a href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/05/25/nhs-hack-day-10/">Cardiff</a>,
before coming back to London in May, and then heading up to Manchester in the Autumn.</p>

<h1>UK Health Camp</h1>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/healthcamp.foyer.jpg" alt="" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->


<p>2015 also saw the first <a href="http://ukhealthcamp.com">UK Health Camp</a> - a community unconference
for people interested in digital and data in health and care. We were proud to sponsor the
event, and glad to have a community space to discuss the pressing issues of digital transformation
within the NHS.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re already looking forward to next year, and have started plotting how to make it even more
of a success with the rest of the team!</p>

<h1>The Future</h1>

<p>Looking forward to to this year, we&rsquo;re excited to be working on lots of new projects, with new
partners, as well as continuing to develop and improve our existing services.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve got a project you think we could help with this year, do drop us a line at
<a href="mailto:hello@openhealthcare.org.uk"><a href="&#109;&#x61;&#105;&#x6c;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#x68;&#101;&#x6c;&#108;&#111;&#64;&#111;&#x70;&#x65;&#x6e;&#x68;&#101;&#97;&#x6c;&#x74;&#x68;&#x63;&#x61;&#x72;&#101;&#46;&#x6f;&#x72;&#x67;&#46;&#x75;&#x6b;">&#x68;&#101;&#x6c;&#x6c;&#x6f;&#64;&#111;&#x70;&#101;&#x6e;&#104;&#x65;&#97;&#x6c;&#x74;&#104;&#x63;&#97;&#114;&#101;&#46;&#x6f;&#x72;&#103;&#x2e;&#x75;&#x6b;</a></a> - we&rsquo;d love to
hear all about it!</p>

<p><small>
Photo credits: <a href="https://secure.flickr.com/photos/paul_clarke/">Paul Clarke</a>
</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2014 - Annual Review]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/01/19/annual-review/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-19T15:00:29+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/01/19/annual-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>OPAL at UCLH</h3>

<p>Early in the year we deployed <a href="http://elcid.openhealthcare.org.uk">elCID</a> - our custom built digital service for
infection doctors to University College London Hospital.</p>

<p>Despite our early plans for a cautious, staggered rollout, demand from end users to transition to the system meant
that we accelerated rapidly, spreading throughout the division of infection at UCLH and racing through the 1000 patient
mark within the few months.</p>

<p>Not content to sit on our laurels, we&rsquo;ve been further developing the platform, with a specialist OPAT (Outpatients
Parenteral Antimicrobial Therapy) service developed and launched early 2015, and a walk-in clinic service scheduled for
deployment in spring.</p>

<h3>OPAL for research</h3>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/elcid.outputs.png" alt="" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->


<p>2014 saw the first academic outputs from the OPAL project, with two posters presented at the
<a href="http://www.fis-infection.org.uk/">Federation of Infection Societies</a> conference.</p>

<p>Demonstrating the new capabilities for conducting clinical audits and exploring hypotheses about the patient
population treated by UCLH, concluding that:</p>

<pre><code>The electronic prospective data capture benefits of elCID have facilitated organisation
and interrogation of our own clinical practice to greater levels than before, describing
many hitherto uncaptured elements of clinical activity.
</code></pre>

<h3>Hackdays</h3>

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/nhshd6.jpg" alt="" />
</div>


<!--//post-thumb-->


<p>2014 saw the <a href="http:/nhshackday.com">NHS Hack Day</a> train roll in to Cardiff, London and Leeds. As ever
the events saw us take multidisciplinary groups of Doctors, Technologists &amp; Patients for a weekend of
furious hacking, resulting not only in some great new projects, but in hundreds of individual opportunities
for people to connect &amp; learn from each other.</p>

<p>Particularly exciting were <a href="https://github.com/huwlynes/tb_care_plan">TB Care Plan</a> - a single page TB guideline
project that managed to take the rule of &ldquo;As simple as it can possibly be&rdquo; to new heights, and a
<a href="https://github.com/openhealthcare/opal-renal">Renal focussed</a> OPAL implementation for handover and patient management.</p>

<h3>The Future</h3>

<p>2014 has been a great year for Open Health Care, &amp; We&rsquo;re excited looking forward to the year to come !</p>

<p>With new product launches, lots of exciting projects in the pipeline, as well as the relentless programme of running
events up &amp; down the country, we&rsquo;ll be busy!</p>

<p><small>
Photo credits: <a href="https://secure.flickr.com/photos/paul_clarke/">Paul Clarke</a> &amp;&amp; <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/gpollara">Gabriel Pollara</a>
</small></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
