<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Elcid | Open Health Care UK - Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/categories/elcid/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/"/>
  <updated>2017-02-20T15:35:44+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Open Health Care UK]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How We're Helping Respond to the Zika Outbreak]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2016/02/16/how-were-helping-respond-to-the-zika-outbreak/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-16T15:00:29+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2016/02/16/how-were-helping-respond-to-the-zika-outbreak</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[The last few months have seen an explosive spread of the
[Zika virus](http://www.theguardian.com/world/2016/jan/28/zika-virus-spreading-explosively-says-world-health-organisation),
which has been potentially linked to thousands of birth defects in Latin America. The Zika virus is a
[mosquito-transmitted infection](http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2016/health/what-is-zika-virus.html)
that was previously sporadically reported in Africa and the Pacific, but has recently started spreading rapidly
in South America. Patients usually have a mild flu-like illness consisting of a low fever, headache, muscle and joint pain,
red eyes and rash.

In the UK, many patients who exhibit symptoms related to Zika and have recently travelled are referred to the specialist
[Hospital for Tropical Diseases](http://www.thehtd.org/) in London, which has resulted in a large increase in their
workload.

The Hospital for Tropical Diseases uses our [elCID](http://elcid.openhealthcare.org.uk/) software to manage their clinical
workflow, so as soon as we heard this,
we tried to understand what we could do to help. At Open Health Care we believe the digital tools clinicians use to do their
jobs need to be iterated and improved on a frequent basis. That means we deliver services that are flexible enough to adapt
to changing clinical needs, and we’re on hand to help make those improvements.

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/zika.top.png" alt="" style="border: 1px solid black;"/>
</div><!--//post-thumb-->

Working closely with clinicians from HTD, we quickly developed a prototype Zika “pathway”. This enables users to record extra
information of particular importance to patients they were treating for Zika, as well as extra quick ways to enter the very
specific set of tests that are most relevant to such patients.

Because we have an electronic clinical pathway specific to the particular condition being treated, we were able to provide
lots of contextually relevant information and notes for its treatment. This guidance was written by the local consultants,
and helps to make sure that every patient is given the very best care possible.

<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/zika.bottom.png" alt="" style="border: 1px solid black;" />
</div><!--//post-thumb-->

All the information about patients that gets entered on [elCID](http://elcid.openhealthcare.org.uk/) is stored as high quality
structured data. That means that we
are also able to generate a summary of their interaction with the patient at the click of a button, complete with
symptoms, travel history, investigations and results, and the specific extra Zika information we are now recording.

Documenting clinical activity in this way - on digital tools that understand the clinical domain -  means that it is also
available subsequently for audit and analysis purposes. Extracting data on the management of Zika patients at the hospital
is now something that can be done in a few clicks, rather than requiring a laborious manual review of clinical documentation.

In many ways this is one of the real opportunities of the NHS’ move to paperless working - when you move to using tools that
allow you to analyse and learn from data generated by routine clinical work. We look forward to finding out what the team
learn about their response to the Zika outbreak.

Crucially, this new module involved just a couple of days prototyping, iterating and testing the new Zika pathway, before
deploying to the live system. Over the next few weeks we’ll be checking back regularly to gather feedback from the users
of the service so that we can be sure that we’re meeting their needs.

Updating the systems that underpin the delivery of care should be this simple all the time - they should be designed with
flexibility and iteration in mind, and be supported by teams who have the capability to iterate them responsively.

If you’d like to know more about how we could help you by delivering services like this, or more about the services we offer,
do get in touch with us at <a href="mailto:hello@openhealthcare.org.uk">hello@openhealthcare.org.uk</a>.

<small>
Photo credits: [John Tan](https://www.flickr.com/photos/31031835@N08/)
</small>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Launching a New Clinical Digital Service for Returning Travellers]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/10/21/launching-a-new-walk-in-service/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-21T21:00:29+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/10/21/launching-a-new-walk-in-service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Just a couple of weeks ago we launched a new service at the [Hospital for Tropical Diseases](http://www.thehtd.org/home.aspx)
in London to help the doctors and nurses who run their [Emergency Walk-In Clinic](http://www.thehtd.org/emergencies.aspx).
At the clinic,
travellers who have returned from the tropics and are acutely unwell turn up without requiring an appointment to get treated
by specialists in tropical diseases. The service tracks patients on their journey through the clinic, from initial triage to
following up on lab results that arrive after they've left.


<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/walkin.referral.png" alt="" style="border: 2px solid black;" />
</div><!--//post-thumb-->

We worked closely with the staff who run the clinic, making sure that we met the different needs of different types of user
- in this case admin staff, the nursing staff, doctors, as well as the service managers who wanted data on what activity was
happening. Just like we do with all of our services, we brought them into our agile development process as we iteratively
developed the service based on research and their feedback.

Clinical digital services too often fail to take into account the experiences of the people on the ground who have to use
them in practice. At Open Health Care we don&#8217;t think that&#8217;s acceptable for something as important as delivering health care.

Because of that we will continue to regularly meet with users of the service to conduct usability testing and actively seek
feedback so that we can continuously improve the service. That feedback loop needs to be a part of the ongoing operation of
digital products and services in hospitals - not just something that happens as part of an initial design phase - and we&#8217;ve
seen before just how useful it can be as we&#8217;ve been able to respond to changing user needs and changes to the context and
processes that surround users experiences of our services.


<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/walkin.nurseledcare.png" alt="" style="border: 2px solid black;" />
</div><!--//post-thumb-->

<h2>Use data to design services.<br>It makes things better</h2>

One of the key goals of the project was to allow the team at HTD to gather high quality data about the cohort of patients
that they treat. This data is hugely valuable, both academically for research purposes, and because it enables the team
to understand their workload.

When the tools that are used for routine day-to-day clinical care don&#8217;t collect usable data, the cost of analysing what you&#8217;ve
been doing become huge. With the new Walk-in service however, all of the information that the institution knows about a patient,
from demographics to observations, travel history to treatment, gets stored as high quality structured data.

That means that anyone can get an accurate answer to a question like &#8220;How many patients did we see with Dengue fever in the last
year&#8221; in seconds, rather than it taking hours or days of painstaking work reviewing case notes, or manually curating and maintaining
their own databases.

We&#8217;re excited about the possibilities for service redesign and research that this new capability has opened up for the team, and
we&#8217;ve already been brainstorming ideas - so watch this space!

## How it all came together

The service was built as a [plugin](https://github.com/openhealthcare/opal-walk-in) for [OPAL](http://opal.openhealthcare.org.uk) -
our open source framework for building high quality digital services in a clinical setting, and is deployed as part of
[elCID - an existing service that we run for UCLH](http://elcid.openhealthcare.org.uk) to manage patients with infection.

We love delivering high quality digital services for doctors.
If you&#8217;d like to explore how we might be able to help you out at your
institution, [get in touch](http://openhealthcare.org.uk/contact.html) - we&#8217;re always keen to meet people with interesting problems
to solve as we try and make sure that the digital services that clinical staff in the NHS use in their day jobs is as good as the
services they use in their personal lives.


<div class="post-thumb">
  <img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/posts/walkin.advice.png" alt="" style="border: 2px solid black;" />
</div><!--//post-thumb-->
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[elCID in the Journal of Infection]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/06/10/elcid-journal-of-infectioncontrol/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-10T21:00:29+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/06/10/elcid-journal-of-infectioncontrol</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[For the past couple of years, Open Health Care has been working in collaboration
with [UCLH](https://www.uclh.nhs.uk/Pages/home.aspx) and the [Hospital for Tropical Diseases](http://www.thehtd.org/)
on [elCID](http://elcid.openhealthcare.org.uk/) (the
electronic Clinical Infection Database) - an Open Source
clinical Digital service for managing inpatients and outpatients with infections.

elCID solves two key clinical problems - first it provides an interface for recording day-to-day
clinical care. We've developed this interface in close collaboration with clinicians with a strong focus on usability,
using [user centred design](https://www.gov.uk/service-manual/user-centred-design) techniques, and
frequent iterations, to make sure that we meet the real needs of our users.

Second, elCID captures structured data about clinical activity, and features advanced
interrogation and extract capabilities. This enables data driven feedback loops in the
design of clinical services, by enabling high quality audits to be conducted much faster
than was ever possible before.

Working with some of the academics who've been instrumental in developing the
project, we recently published an analysis of the early findings from this process in the
<a href="http://www.journalofinfection.com/article/S0163-4453(15)00100-0/abstract">Journal of Infection</a>.

As the paper outlines:

<blockquote class="custom-quote"><p><i class="fa fa-quote-left"></i>
elCID brings together disparate silos of clinical data collection into a single, rapidly searchable database resource permitting unprecedented interrogation of our clinical practice. <br />
However, the benefits of the system go further, having vastly improved the quality and transparency of communication between the Division’s teams, audits of day-to-day clinical practice are now rapidly and routinely performed using high quality prospectively collected data, and research study data collection can be conducted within the main database, facilitating improved integration of the clinical and academic arms of the Division.
</p></blockquote>

elCID is an Open Source, Open Governance project built on the Open Source [OPAL](http://opal.openhealthcare.org.uk/)
framework. It is available to infection services and comes with full support and customisation from Open Health Care.
You can find out more information about the software on the [elCID website](http://elcid.openhealthcare.org.uk/).

If you&#8217;re interested in seeing how elCID might help at your organisation, or if you&#8217;d
like a copy of the full paper, don&#8217;t hesitate to drop us a line at [hello@openhealthcare.org.uk](hello@openhealthcare.org.uk)
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How Doctors Get Digital Services They Love]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/03/11/how-doctors-get-digital-services-they-love/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-11T21:12:19+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/03/11/how-doctors-get-digital-services-they-love</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[At Open Health Care, we believe in
[User-centered design](https://www.gov.uk/service-manual/user-centred-design).

Which means that we focus on meeting the needs of our users, and is why we
always work in close collaboration with them. Whether that comes in the
form of making sure that our clinical champions are present at every sprint
meeting, or working hard to get clinical staff and patients along to
[NHS Hack Day](http://nhshackday.com) we work by putting users first, building
and testing in small chunks.

Working this way means that generally when we work on a project, we identify
clinical champion(s) for that project. These are the kind of people who will use the service
we end up building in their day-to-day work. In order to get them as involved as
possible, we introduce them to [Agile](https://www.gov.uk/service-manual/agile),
and we often find ourselves teaching [doctors](https://github.com/GabPoll) to
[github](https://github.com/michaeledwardmarks). (Yes, that's a verb now).

The great thing about working in multidisciplinary teams, is that *everyone* learns
new things, all the time. For every medical three letter acronym like say,
[CAP](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Community-acquired_pneumonia) that gets explained
to a developer, there's an explanation of what
[API](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Application_programming_interface) stands for that goes the
other way.

But it's not just terminology that gets shared - often we try to share our tools. We
promote online
[collaborative](http://www.google.co.uk/docs/about/)
[document](http://hackpad.com/) editing above email attachments and
[naming conventions](http://thedoghousediaries.com/5964). We encourage users to take
up better web browsers. We get them to try out modern
[team communication](https://slack.com/) [tools](http://appear.in), and recommend [Open Source](http://www.rstudio.com/)
alternatives to the proprietary default incumbents.

### But wait - it gets better

Not only does this help us all understand one another better, which is so vital to delivering
high quality digital services, but it also often introduces clinicians to tools that reward
power users with advanced functionality. Once you've learnt
[markdown](https://help.github.com/articles/github-flavored-markdown/) once, typing information
into text boxes that will get rendered in a web browser is never quite the same again. You start
*expecting* that the web based [clinical digital services](http://opal.openhealthcare.org.uk)
you use in your day job let you [use markdown](https://github.com/openhealthcare/opal/blob/823de649ddee6c13803264d929ece3ae171104c5/opal/static/js/opal/opaldown.js)
there too.

Possibly the best feature we've implemented that came about this way is the
[OPAL ](http://opal.openhealthcare.org.uk)
Macros from
late last year. Directly inspired by [Github issue mentions](https://github.com/blog/957-introducing-issue-mentions),
OPAL Macros let the user define blocks of commonly used text, and then insert them with shortcut Macros -
(names preceded by the # symbol).

For instance, for [Staph](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Staphylococcus_aureus) advice, the user enters #st:

<img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/features/macro.pre.png" alt="" />

&#8230; which then expands to the (institutionally defined) standard advice for this case:

<img class="img-responsive" src="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/assets/images/features/macro.post.png" alt="" />

This is the kind of user need that only even comes up when users are digitally literate enough to
be able to express it - something along the lines of:

<blockquote class="custom-quote"><p><i class="fa fa-user-md fa-3x"></i>
As a Doctor <br />
I want to avoid repeatedly typing out standard advice <br />
So that I can spend more time with my patients
</p></blockquote>

The existence of this kind of power-user functionality encourages users to master their tools, by
offering them time savings and efficiencies but crucially, doesn&#8217;t interfere with the user experience at all if you
don&#8217;t know it&#8217;s there. As
[Dr Marks](https://github.com/michaeledwardmarks), who had originally explained the need on
Github said:

<blockquote class="custom-quote"><p><i class="fa fa-quote-left"></i>
Absolutely stunning.<br/>
I would say this is one of the most incredible things I have seen on a piece of NHS software ever.
</p></blockquote>

If you&#8217;re interested in starting an OPAL project at your institution to take advantage of this kind
of feature, or in seeing how we can can help you by providing clinical facing digital services,
don&#8217;t hesitate to [Get in touch](/contact.html)!

<small>
Photo credits: <br />
[Jacopo Romei](http://www.flickr.com/photos/jakuza/)<br />
</small>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[elCID OPAT Launched at UCLH]]></title>
    <link href="http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/02/05/elcid-opat-launch/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-05T09:12:19+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://openhealthcare.org.uk/blog/2015/02/05/elcid-opat-launch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Last week saw us excited to launch our new [OPAT](http://e-opat.com/) (Outpatients
Parenteral Antimicrobial Therapy) service delivered via the [elCID](http://elcid.openhealthcare.org.uk)
platform at UCLH.

This is the first deployment of the specialist OPAT module for [OPAL](http://opal.openhealthcare.org.uk) -
our Open Source framework for building transactional digital services. It covers the whole range of an
OPAT service - from initial referrals and assessment, through ongoing care, post-treatment follow up and
review. All of the workflows capture high quality data at the time of use, and allow analysis and extraction,
both for reporting in line with national guidelines, and individual service audits.

As ever, we worked closely with clinical champions, who were deeply involved in the agile development process,
weighing in on [GitHub](https://github.com/openhealthcare/elcid/issues), attending sprint meetings, and
providing their expertise to our development team. The whole project is released under an Open Source (GPL)
license, and was developed in the open.


This was a project we loved delivering, and not just because of the high praise from Dr Jon Lambourne, UCLH's
clinical lead on the project, who said:

<blockquote class="custom-quote"><p><i class="fa fa-quote-left"></i>
The Open Health Care team have been super, the things they can get the OPAL software to do regularly leaves me slack-jawed!
</p></blockquote>

While we like to think that we&#8217;re pretty good at executing on the technology side of things, it&#8217;s really the collaboration
between us and the clinical users, along with our focus on their needs that makes it possible for us to deliver
new user-focussed digital services into the world.

Accordingly, we&#8217;d particularly like to thank
[Dr Sarah Logan](https://www.uclh.nhs.uk/OurServices/Consultants/Pages/DrSarahLogan.aspx) (Our consultant sponsor),
[Steve Collins](https://github.com/7575colli) (OPAT Nurse extraordinaire), and
[Dr Jon Lambourne](https://github.com/jonnylambourne) (Clinical lead on the project) for all their efforts.

If you&#8217;re interested in seeing an OPAL project at your institution, or in seing how we can can
support running clinical OPAT services, don&#8217;t hesitate to [Get in touch](/contact.html)!

<small>
Photo Credits: [Lydia](https://www.flickr.com/photos/lydiashiningbrightly/5922822998)
</small>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
